<preface id="preface">
   <title>Preface</title>

   <para>
      This is the official JBoss Cache Users' Guide. Along with its accompanying documents (an FAQ, a tutorial and a
      whole set of documents on POJO Cache), this is freely available on the JBoss Cache <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosscache">documentation website</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
      When used, JBoss Cache refers to JBoss Cache Core, a tree-structured, clustered, transactional cache.
      POJO Cache, also a part of the JBoss Cache distribution, is documented separately. (POJO Cache is a cache that
      deals with Plain Old Java Objects, complete with object relationships, with the ability to cluster such POJOs
      while maintaining their relationships. Please see the POJO Cache documentation for more information about this.)
   </para>

   <para>
      This book is targeted at developers wishing to use JBoss Cache as either a standalone in-memory cache,
      a distributed or replicated cache, a clustering library, or an in-memory database.  It is targeted at application
      developers who wish to use JBoss Cache in their code base, as well as "OEM" developers who wish to build on and
      extend JBoss Cache features. As such, this book is split into two major sections - one detailing the "User" API
      and the other going much deeper into specialist topics and the JBoss Cache architecture.
   </para>

   <para>
      In general, a good knowledge of the Java programming language along with a strong appreciation and understanding
      of transactions and concurrent programming is necessary. No prior knowledge of JBoss Application Server is expected
      or required.
   </para>

   <para>
      For further discussion, use the user forum available on the JBoss Cache
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosscache">website.</ulink>  We also provide a mechanism for
      tracking bug reports and feature requests on the JBoss Cache <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.com/jira/browse/JBCACHE">JIRA issue tracker</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
      If you are interested in the development of JBoss Cache or in translating this documentation into other languages,
      we'd love to hear from you. Please post a message on the JBoss Cache
      <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosscache">user forum</ulink>
      or contact us by using the JBoss Cache <ulink url="https://lists.jboss.org/mailman/listinfo/jbosscache-dev">developer mailing list</ulink>.
   </para>

   <para>
      This book is specifically targeted at the JBoss Cache release of the same version number. It may not apply to
      older or newer releases of JBoss Cache. It is important that you use the documentation appropriate to the version
      of JBoss Cache you intend to use.
   </para>

   <para>
      I always appreciate feedback, suggestions and corrections, and these should be directed to the
      <ulink url="https://lists.jboss.org/mailman/listinfo/jbosscache-dev">developer mailing list</ulink> rather than
      direct emails to any of the authors.  We hope you find this book useful, and wish you happy reading!
   </para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Manik Surtani</emphasis>, October 2008
   </para>
</preface>